<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a Member of the House of Commons, to a gentleman now at London, touching the new Solemne League and Covenant.</title>
            <author>Member of the House of Commons.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E45_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154485</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154485)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E45[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a Member of the House of Commons, to a gentleman now at London, touching the new Solemne League and Covenant.</title>
                  <author>Member of the House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154485:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER From A MEMBER OF THE HOVSE OF COMMONS, To a Gentleman now at London, touching the New <hi>Solemne</hi> LEAGUE and COVENANT.</p>
            <p>OXFORD, <hi>Printed by</hi> H. Hall. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:154485:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154485:2"/>
            <head>A Letter from a Member of the Houſe of Commons, to a Gentleman now at <hi>London,</hi> touching the New <hi>Solemne League and Covenant.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's no wonder, but common experience, that the diviſion of King and People (ſo deſtructive to publique peace and private happineſſe) drawes with it the breach of all relations: for when the foundation of publique order is ſubverted, we may ſoone expect the fractions of families and friends, (bonds ſacred in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) the late ſtrangeneſſe betweene us ariſing from our different wayes in the preſent diſtractions is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which yet may not withhold me from expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating your taking the new Covenant, and preaching with much vehemency (as is affirmed) the neceſſity of taking it by others. I ſhall not looke backe on the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of your engagement to that party, who have thus advanced themſelves; though I conceive the cleareneſſe of your judgement muſt diſcerne the unſoundneſſe of theſe grounds that were layed for taking up Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, and that you could not ſecure your conſcience in partaking with ſuch blacke deſignes by principles, which conſtitute the King onely paſſive in government,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154485:3"/>and that he muſt ſic as an idle Spectator of the diſorders and miſeries of his Subjects, and thinke his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count well diſcharged towards God and Man, if he leave all to the Counſells of others, without his owne deliberation or triall of them by Scripture or reaſon. Surely the charge of a Prince is not ſo weighty, if this be the greateſt burden, nor his finall account in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſo terrible, neither were the prayers for him ſo neceſſary in reſpect of his people depending on him, as the Scriptures aſſure us, if their good or evill were ſo little concerned in him. Your former reſolutions not to conforme to humane Lawes in any thing, wherein your conſcience was unſatisfied of divine authority, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not to inforce others to repeale lawes by the ſword, which they are perſwaded were a ſinfull diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God and his Vicegerent. And unleſſe your paſſions have darkened your judgement, and made you impatient of contradiction, though from your owne or the moſt undenyable principles of divine truth, I may hope you will ſatisfie or eaſe a doubting conſcience, in this your Covenant. And firſt upon view of the Title, being a <hi>ſolemne League and Covenant</hi> amongſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects without, as much as a royall aſſent: or authority of law, without which all agreements to alter religion or government are a knowne high treaſon. I find moſt men though farre engaged on your party, ſtand amazed, how they can defend religion by treaſon, how they can breake the ſupreame lawes of government, without breach of duty to God, fidelity to his Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, or peace of conſcience. I have not yet found any anſwer to this, unleſſe it be expected that our preſident of violence may aſwell iuſtify, as cauſe another.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154485:3"/>
            <p>But it ſeemes the end of this Covenant is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of its legality, and being <hi>for Reformation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of religion,</hi> &amp;c. The Lawes of civill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt give place to it. A Poſition which I ſtill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, till of late, the peculiar of the Jeſuits; and if that be the ſupport of your Covenant, the affinity it hath with that ſect, ſhould at leaſt render it ſuſpected, if not hated by your ſelfe: but the oppoſition it hath to the practice of Chriſtians in all ages, the ſcandall it gives to the cauſe of religion, by ſhaking all govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments where it's entertained, make it odious to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that deſire the union of truth and peace.</p>
            <p>The name of <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>defence of religion</hi> hath ſeldome beene wanting to any rebellion, the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of which crime ſeeke to lurke under the moſt plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible pretences. And as I plainely ſee by this Covenant not reformation or defence but alteration and introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is avowed, and there is no invaſion or violence, but may uſurpe the title of defence, if alteration of lawes &amp; government by force againſt the mind of the Prince, be ſuch. Therefore the penners of this Covenant wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omitted lawes, out of the particulars to be defended by this Covenant, in the Title, which muſt caſt ſhame on the front ſo contradictory to them.</p>
            <p>The next end, <hi>the honour and happineſſe of the King,</hi> whether ſincerely intended, I appeale to your ſelfe, or any that take this Covenant, whether the maine Scope be not to take away his iuſt authority, diveſt him of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and place all, or the principall parts of Majeſtie in others, without whom he ſhall be diſabled to reſiſt any rebell or enemy: if this be a truth, as I thinke it's known to the moſt common underſtanding, you will ſtand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154485:4"/>guilty to God, aſwell of groſſe hypocriſy, as diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and I ſhould gladly know what honour is meant the King, that ſhall be reduced to ſuch a condition. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve few forraigne Princes will underſtand ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of much honour, and they will quickely find it of leſſe power; and that the peace and ſafety of the three Kingdomes will be kept by this Covenant, when the Soveraigne power, the band of union is diſſolved, I may rather dreame then beleeve.</p>
            <p>To the preamble, that makes the <hi>danger of Religion,</hi> the motive of this Covenant, whoſoever lookes on the progreſſe of the preſent diſtractions, and by what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees they roſe, that ſees the credit and imployment that Sectaries and Schiſmatiques of all ſorts have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe Covenanters, that ſuch, as in the cleereſt and moſt unſuſpected times were branded for diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of Church and State, now undertooke to declare them enemies to Religion, that have beene the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of Gods cauſe againſt the common enemies of our Religion, (if Papiſts are ſo intended by this Covenant) that ſees by whom Armies have beene raiſed, Townes taken, the King purſued, will find plots againſt the true Religion and the profeſſors thereof, under the maske of defending it, and all the miſeries raiſed in the three Kingdomes, to take their originall from theſe Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who, while they violently acted their deſignes in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> defrauded <hi>Ireland</hi> of neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife, and caſt it into that infelicity it ſo long groan'd under.</p>
            <p>The commendable practice of thoſe Kingdomes in former times, and the example of Gods people in other Nations, is of weight, if the allegation were of credit,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154485:4"/>and the times had beene pointed out, that we might have beene informed of their certainety and authority. I have heard of the <hi>unholy league</hi> in <hi>France</hi> to reſiſt <hi>Henry</hi> the 4 of that Kingdome, if he ſubmitted not to the Roman religion: if that be one of your examples, as it hath great likeneſſe to your preſent Covenant, (and difference of true and falſe Religion makes not a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the legality of Armes againſt the Prince, which are rebelliouſly borne, if againſt him or his lawes, and you well know there is no law to alter Religion againſt the will of the King.) I ſhall not deny you the truth, but leave you the ſtrength of that example.</p>
            <p>There was an attempt of the Papiſts, neare the death of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to oppoſe any ſucceſſor not of their Religion: I remember but theſe that are ſo well like your caſe, and I beleeve there are none nearer in this or other kingdomes.</p>
            <p>The firſt article, <hi>to endeavour the preſervation of the reformed religion, in the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip, Diſipline, and Government againſt our common enemies,</hi> carrieth ſuch doubtfull ſence, as I may juſtly ſuſpect it, rather a ſnare to entangle, then a rule to guide the Conſcience. It is not onely raſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, but irreligious prophaneneſſe, to ſweare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of unknowne precepts: and the Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> are knowne to few that take this Oath, who with an implicit faith ſweare to preſerve they know not what, perhaps that, which if they knew, they would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſire to deſtroy. I thinke your ſelfe would not ſweare to preſerve the Doctrines, &amp;c. of all the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches, and I am ſure, no law bindes me to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154485:5"/>this, and Chriſtian duty forbids me to ſweare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that which I know not, which may be ſinfull in it ſelfe, and muſt needs be ſinne to him who ſweares in ignorance, ſo much more to them that enforce it on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and whereof God will one day require an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. And they, who formerly found the Canons of the late Convocation ſo full of exception, have herein juſtified them, and given all the offence they tooke at theſe Canons, and much more, in the injuſtice of this oath; being of things unknowne, of an other Church and Nation, of Diſcipline and Government which are of humane inſtitution, and perhaps oppoſite to our owne fundamentall lawes, diſhonourable to our Church and Nation, and deſtructive to both; a matter of worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, then the late &amp;c. and your ſelfe, if I heare truly, are much departed from your former reſolutions, that thought ſubſcription ſhould be forborne to ſome tender conſciences, and now judge there is no pretence for avoyding this Covenant, that hath not only doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes but apparent danger of perjury and preſumption, and in compariſon whereof the moſt rigid of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Canons was a moſt innocent and tender Injunction.</p>
            <p>I inquire not why <hi>Scotland</hi> may not be reformed, why <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> muſt, but why in doctrine, I pray demand of theſe that have acknowledged the ſoundneſſe of it by their oathes and preachinge and when that famous and conſcientious Doctor <hi>Reynolds</hi> and others at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court moved a reformation of ſome things in Ceremony and Clergy, they openly profeſſed their unqueſtionable aſſent to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the thirty nine Articles, and the oath of Supremacy (which how obſerved in this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154485:5"/>Covenant undertaken without the King, and to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without reſpect to him, is ſeene of all.) I may more then ſuſpect theſe new reformers are not of our Church, that deny her Doctrine, and that theſe men, who had no conſcience in their former ſubſcriptions, will not expreſſe any in their reformation. The rule they pretend is the word of God, with an addition of the example of the beſt reformed Churches. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the example of other Churches is not the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone whereby we muſt try doctrine or worſhip, it ſeems the word of God will not doe the worke theſe men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, they will herein allow the ſuperſtructure of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and they are contented to exclude the example of the primitive Church, (a name venerable to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and in all true Chriſtian Churches;) and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their mother, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by other Churches, where neither the word of God, nor primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive practice covince her of errour, is farre from the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſonnes and Charity of Chriſtians. I conceive the word [beſt reformed] will beget a Schiſme, rather then cloſe the breach of the reformed Churches, and while we expreſſe our eſteeme of ſome, in ſuch language, as upbrayds others with defects, we provoke their juſt complaint againſt us. There is not any reformed Church that I have heard of that accounts it ſelfe worſe then other in their confeſſions of doctrine, and therefore ſome will be undoubtedly ſcandalized by this expreſſion and a faction raiſed among our ſelves, while every man takes, [beſt reformed,] in his owne ſence; and the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration being of ſo great variety of circumſtances, when ſome that are accounted beſt in government may be worſt in doctrine, and the contrary, it muſt prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154485:6"/>to the conſcience, and an uneven rule to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Church. We may depend on Gods promiſe, that he will dwell among us, that have one faith, one baptiſme, one Lord Jeſus Chriſt who died for us, and if in matters of forme and circumſtances of government we differ, and yet retaine the unity of ſpirit in the bond of peace, as is our duty, we may be aſſured he will ſtill delight to doe ſoe, rather then in the cauſeles rents for indifferent things. But the uſe theſe men make of ſcripture is for phraſe, not for proofe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the extirpation of Popery, Superſtition, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie, Schiſme, and prophaneneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound doctrine, and the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of godlineſſe, you have an univerſall conſent, that it's fit to be done by every one as he hath the warrant of a lawfull calling to it. But why Prelacy, &amp;c. that hath the authority of longeſt continuance, and practice in the firſt and beſt ages of the Church of God, of legall eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment in this Kingdome, that hath beene eminent for the Learning, Piety, Zeale, and Martyrdome of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in theſe Orders, and from whom we muſt in a great part by Gods great bleſſing, acknowledge the happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in this Church, may juſtly be demanded, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny among us, as many doe, conceive this government as neceſſary to continue, as you doe to be deſtroyed, will you not put as great a burden upon their conſcience in preſſing it in this Covenant, as you imagine upon your owne by the continuance of this government? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more, for your Covenant in this very point is a breach of duty, being a plaine and wilfull reſiſtance of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers, and not only contempt, but ſubverſion of Lawes.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154485:6"/>
            <p>Sir, I have no intent to travell into controverſies, but the Lord was and will be one, and his name one in the three Kingdomes, if this government continue; and I am ſure a Covenant to take it away againſt the mind of the Prince, while it thus ſtandes by law, is rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his Vicegerent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It might move any man to juſt indignation that reads your oſtentations of loyalty, when the very act you doe and the formes of publiſhing theſe words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the contrary. I am ſure the King is not conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, no reſervation made of his conſent in this very thing that is thus impoſed on all his Subiects, and the World that is called to witneſſe will teſtifie, loyalty is ſpoken, treaſon acted. And I appeale to your ſelfe, with what ingenuity the defence of the Kings Perſon is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, the words are [defend the Kings Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and authority, in the preſervation and defence of the true religion &amp;c.] I pray obſerve the evaſions of this profeſſion, they will defend the Kings Perſon in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence &amp;c. that is the defence of Religion is the defence of his Perſon and Authority, ſo as if they defend religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp;c. in heir owne ſenſes, they defend him, though they deſtroy him. Or if that evaſion be not ſubtile enough, they have another, they will defend him &amp;c. whiles he preſerves and defends religion; both which equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons theſe words admit, no plaine meaning at all. I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelfe it was fitted purpoſely to avoyd the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of loyalty without condition, or ambiguity, and by theſe cautelous ſhiftes, it's evident they intend no ſubjection to any Chriſtian Prince who is not of their owne opinions.</p>
            <p>For the diſcovery of ſuch as have divided the King
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154485:7"/>and his people, or one of the Kingdomes from another, all the world hath diſcovered theſe Covenanters to be the men, who have made ſo many Declarations againſt the King, divided him and his people, denying his juſt authority, and forbidding his Subjects bounden duty to him, and if any man hath beene a cauſe that the King hath denyed any juſtice or right to his people, I ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that part of this covenant into my private practice, to diſcover him, but I ſhall never thinke him Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Malignant, or evill Inſtrument, that ſhall aſſiſt him for preſervation of his perſon and rights, and defend him againſt any that ſhall demand his conſent to any thing by Armes, as is now done by this Covenant. For the Kingdomes, they are in themſelves naturally and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally divided; what diviſions of affections have beene wrought among the people, hath proceeded from the wayward paſſions of theſe men, that againſt all order nature and duty make an independent Kingdome, their native Country ſubject to the Subjects of another Kingdome, nay two Kingdomes to one, in whoſe laws they have no intereſt, deſtroy their owne lawes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive anothers, and cut aſunder the band of all union, the power of the Prince, in all his Kingdomes. And herein I would gladly know, what the fault is of doing contrary to this Covenant, for certainely the crime as well as the puniſhment, is a ſtranger to law; and what conſcience is left in theſe men, that puniſh without law, God will one day reveale; in the meane time, I ſee that law is no longer practiced by them, then it ſerves pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It was lately our happineſſe, that we enjoyed the bleſſing of peace betweene theſe Kingdomes, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154485:7"/>our progenitors wanted, and poſterity may; we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre that peace, by Gods bleſſing, to our union under one King: but when we take away that band, and place the Soveraignty in divided bodies, we may not long reſt ſecure of that former happineſſe; and the alteration of this firſt article from the firſt edition, is an evill omen which leaves out the obſervance of the late treaty, and of juſtice to be done upon the oppoſers, which makes me thinke, they allready lay plots for retaining theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy diviſions, which were formerly ſo hereditary to theſe Nations.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The reſolution of conſtancy in this evill cauſe, as it makes the cure of the preſent miſeries of this nation; ſo theſe men they were deſperate, who bind themſelves againſt their King and nation, and diſavow all repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and remorſe of conſcience, for the evill they have done.</p>
            <p>Sir, Having thus expreſſed my ſenſe of your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, I ſhall, on occaſion of it, digreſſe to give you the ſtate of the preſent buſineſſe, accounted a controverſie ſo great, as nothing but the ſword is likely to decide, which I thinke a mind free from prejudice and paſſion would ſoone reſolve.</p>
            <p>I am confident your ſelfe never doubted, that there was a neceſſity of the Kings perſonall conſent, called the royall aſſent, to every act of Parliament. And that it could not binde without ſuch aſſent; that the King had the ſame power over his Townes; Caſtles, Ships, and Subjects, ſitting a Parliament, as when it ſate not; that it is high treaſon in any Members of Parliament to make warre upon the King, or his Subjects, or to take his Townes, or any part of his Dominions, aſwell ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154485:8"/>a Parliament, as not. If any of this be denied, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of time, as farre as practice hath proofe, beſides the teſtimony of law, as farre as it's knowne, makes it unqueſtionable. From hence I proceed, that if the two Houſes of Parliament, declare a thing neceſſary for the Kingdome, being a fact, and therefore onely probable, and wherein they are ſubject to errour, the Kings diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſhall not give a power unto the Houſes, to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ordinance without him to binde the people. This is a truth ſo undoubted, that he holds his Crowne but <hi>ad placitum</hi> of the Houſes, if they have ſuch a power. Theſe premiſes I pray take into your thoughts, &amp; ſatisfy your friends, what you have againſt any of them; and if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, then I am ſure the taking, fortifying and keeping Townes againſt the King, commanding the Militia without him, and raiſing Armes to defend the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made for it, are illegall and high treaſon without contradiction: That Armes were raiſed for defence of theſe Ordinances before they were invaded, I cannot thinke any man doubts, and therefore ſome will juſtify theſe Armes for taking Delinquents, that is, ſuch as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the King upon his command. I never yet heard any deny, that theſe Delinquents were pardonable, if faulty, and to be proſecuted for the King only, &amp; that no Court in which capacity is the Lords Houſe, or Houſe of Commons, ſends for any, can uſe any other power for their apprehenſion, or ſuppreſſing oppoſition, but the ordinary officers of law and juſtice, and in caſe of their want, or weakeneſſe, they have recourſe onely to the royall power, reſident in the perſon of the King. And I never knew yet a deniall of this truth; and it is as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that the Members of Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:154485:8"/>having thus raiſed theſe Armies, and expelled all from their counſells that concurre not with them, that admit forraigne counſells, inſtead of the royall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that require a Covenant from their Members to repeale eſtabliſhed lawes, and in caſe of refuſall expell them, that awe their Members with Armies, Tumults, and Threats, that have called in ſtrangers to invade the Kingdome, are thereby no longer a Parliament, having taken away all freedome from it, and the King to come to it, but on their conditions; and hence you ſee where to referre the effuſion of ſo much Chriſtian bloud, and all other miſeries of this nation.</p>
            <p>Sir, Though your confidence be great in the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Houſes, yet weigh impartially their proceedings, &amp; you will ſee the condition they have put themſelves in, is not of Subjects, and conſequently are not their Kings Parliament, which they muſt be, or none at all.</p>
            <p>I conclude with your Covenant, that our great and crying ſinnes have brought this evill upon us, that our preſent calamity is a ſcourge from Heaven, and yet theſe wicked hands by whom God afflictes a people, eſcape not his revenge of their treachery, cruelty and injuſtice. We have enjoyed the free uſe of our religion, the land was covered with knowledge as the waters co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the ſea, forraigne Churches rejoyced in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our order, conſtancy and increaſe and all eminent gifts, yet we deſpiſe our Church, caſt off the guides thereof as Antichriſtian, heape to our ſelves multitudes of Ignorant Teachers, pleaſe our ſelves beſt with theſe that take pleaſure in deſpiſing dominion, and ſpeaking evill of dignities; calumnies, diſgraces and libells againſt thoſe that were ſet over us, are cheifely affected by us;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154485:9"/>theſe were the ſeedes of the preſent rebellion by which God viſits theſe and our other ſinnes upon us: for aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of whoſe wrath we muſt all confeſſe our owne, and the ſinnes of our nation, and by timely repentance and ſincere reformation of life, turne and cry mightily unto the Lord, that he will heare, and forgive, and heale the land.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
